- ✓ Email: boven.ellen@gmail.com
- ✓ Date of Birth: 8th March 1993
- ✓ Place of Birth: Ghent, Belgium

Professional interest

I am passionate about research at the intersection of experimental and computational neuroscience. In my PhD, I use artificial neural networks alongside experimental neuroscience in rodents to understand cerebrocerebellar network function during learning. I strongly believe that the interplay between modern experimental techniques and basic observations of behaviour embedded in a strong theoretical framework is crucial for advancing neuroscience and Al research

Skills



Rodent behavioral training, chemogenetics, stereotactic surgery, immunohistochemistry, computational modelling, deep learning models, data analysis withmodels and rodent data, data visualization ,two-photon calcum imaging, confocal imaging, electrophysiology



Python, Matlab, R statistics, PyTorch, Pandas, Jupyter notebook, google colab, Matplotlib/Seaborn, LaTex



Motivated, teamwork, academic writing, reporting and presenting

English, Dutch (both at native level), French and Spanish

Musician, guitarist, BrainInspired podcast

Ellen Boven

Education

PhD in Neuroscience | 2018-2022 University of Bristol, UK

M.S. Neuroscience, magna cum laude | 2015-2017 Antwerp University, BE

Eramsus Program | 2014 – 2015 University of Bordeaux, FR

Bachelor in Biology | 2011 – 2014 Ghent University, BE

Research positions

PhD thesis, advised by Rui Ponte Costa and Richard Apps | 2018 – 2022
Cerebro-cerebellar interactions for temporal information processing
Research assistant, advised by Michael Häusser | 2017 – 2018
Decision coding by layer 2/3 neurons in primary somatosensory cortex
Master dissertation, advised by Michael Giugliano | 2016-2017

Master dissertation, advised by Michele Giugliano | 2016-2017 Intracellular calcium dynamics reflect network-level electrophysiology in a in vitro model of developing microcircuitry

Undergraduate student, advised by Marc Cruts | 2016
Identification of genetic modifiers of onset age in frontotemporal dementia
Bachelor thesis, advised by Bart Braeckman | 2014
The role of protein turnover during ageing in *C. elegans*

Papers

- ✓ Boven, E., Pemberton, J., Chadderton, P. et al. Cerebro-cerebellar networks facilitate learning through feedback decoupling. Nat Commun 14, 51 (2023). https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-022-35658-8 J. Pemberton*, E. Boven*, P. Chadderton, R. Apps, R.P. Costa. Cortico-cerebellar networks as decoupling neural interfaces. NeurIPS (2021)
- ✓ L.Y. Prince, E. Boven, R. H. Eyono, A. Ghosh, J. Pemberton, F. Scherr, C. Clopath, R. P. Costa, W. Maass, B. A. Richards, C. Savin C, K. A. Wilmes. CCN GAC Workshop: Isuees with learning in biological recurrent neural networks (2021). NBDT
- Buetfering, C., Zhang, Z., Pitsiani, M., Smallridge, J., Boven, E., McElligott, S. & Hausser, M. Behaviorally relevant decision coding in primary somatosensory cortex neurons. <u>Nat Neurosci</u> 25, 1225–1236 (2022). https://doi.org/10.1038/s41593-022-01151-0
- ✓ Boven E & Giugliano M (2019). Correlating calcium dynamics with network activity in an in vitro model of a cortical microcircuitry. <u>Front. Neurosci.</u> Conference Abstract: 12th National Congress of the Belgian Society for Neuroscience. doi: 10.3389/conf.fnins.2017.94.00071

Research Funding

4-year Wellcome Trust Studentship in Neural Dynamics (2018-2022) European Commission ERASMUS+ traineeship (2017-2018)

Conferences - organisation teams - talks

POSTERS - 2022: FENS & COSYNE - 2021: ChampalimaudResearch Symposium, COSYNE - 2020: Neuromatch - 2019: SfN TEAMS - 2021: wwNeuRise seminar - 2020: postgraduate equality diversity and inclusivity representative - 2017: CNS conference volunteer TALKS - 2022: Gao lab (ERASMUS MC) - 2021: Wagner lab (NIH)